topic uh today uh the advanced topic on
n and ASR and I will uh explain about
several kind of techniques uh that
improve the ASR or the application of
the end to end as so uh today uh the
mostly the spending time for the
MultiLing ASR but before that I will
start the data orentation so uh the as
you know speech data have a lot of Vari
ations uh of course you know it comes
from the uh the uh our uh the the
natures like you know the speaker
characteristics or the emotion and so on
uh which is not easy to
argument however uh other part is
actually can be easily
augumented uh one of the uh the the
issue is that noise that is uh that
actually quite critically degrade our
speech performance and the room impulse
response is also another big factor
which actually makes the speech to have
a reverberation Echo and then this also
degrade the performance these two are
the most the
difficult the component in the speech uh
recognition and another is the speaking
style uh that's like for example
sometimes people speaking
uh the very quickly or some people are
speaking the slowly and so on and
fortunately these three component are
actually uh the imitated uh easily and
especially the the first two noise room
impulse response is actually can be uh
the imitated by the simulation and the
speaking Style this is actually just
changing the uh the the uh the speed uh
which can be also easily controlled by
the several audio processing tools and
so on so these are the three are
actually quite other the the uh the
widely they tackled by based on the data
augmentation and especially uh noise uh
room impulse response is actually
luckily we have a very the uh the
property which is the uh how to call it
the
uh wave form uh the additive property of
the wave form uh yeah I think this is
fine there are several technical word
yeah I forgot the waveform has a
additive additivity right are the sound
a and sound B are the adding and then we
just the this becomes a mixed signal
right uh just uh the adding the up yeah
just adding the the two uh wave form and
then we can actually making the noisy
data it sounds like very obvious right
but the this is not for the other media
like a text and image and so on the
speech luckily has this kind of a uh the
nature uh and the same for the room
impulse response and then generally uh
the this uh the uh
the uh the the the process is written by
this very simple equation uh X is the
original signal and R is the room
impulse response which we can actually
record it uh by the in the quiet the
room bequ rooms well we can actually
simulate the room impulse response by
the simulator
and so on and the uh noise uh we can
again also recording many noises right
and then uh how we do it is we just
following this equation and then we can
actually creating the barriers uh the
the noisy speech noisy and rant speech
and then uh still you know uh this is
the speech so we have a corresponding
transcription right so in is just
augmented and we can actually train the
many variation of the noise many
variation of the room impulse response
and then we can actually make speech con
to be robust against this kind of a
changes and so on uh by the way this is
a very straightforward but the most
important technique all our kind of
other speech recognizer for example the
Google home or the Amazon Alexa first
starting from this
process and then the doing some more
fancy stuff like you know denoting or
the separation or something like that uh
that this kind of fany stuff Happ
happens but before that we always have
this kind of the data augmentation step
and then uh the our current technology
exist okay so uh let's uh show you the
uh play some of the example let for
example this is a queen speech hope it
not be super
large a word should be said here of the
title of Dante's
autobiography this is just a cleen
speech I can put it
again a word should be said here of the
title of Dante's
autobiography next I just kind of taking
the noise only data from the the free
sound some water sound maybe the
bathroom I'm not sure but I just got it
from the the
free next
[Applause]
[Music]
one some jungle not
sure and then of course you know uh we
might have some situation that you know
we will that want to use the speech in
Jungle and so on right but it's not easy
to collect such data right don't worry
we can just you know the argument data
so like for example the first cases a
word should be said here of the title of
that is
autobiography we just adding them uh but
it's actually you know there's one
parameter there are several parameter
but one of the parameter is actually
control the game and then making a noise
to be louder or smaller because that's
also affecting the performance and then
you know neural network knows this kind
of variation they could actually learn
that so A word should be said
here it's almost I cannot hear that
rather it's a good example for neural
network to train the model right
and the same for
the word should be here
title again not sure it happens but we
can create this kind of a conditions and
this methodology can be you know the use
for many of the situations if we have
some specific noises in our application
so on we can collect them in advance and
then using the this equation and just
adding them and then we can or the data
and so on but the last are the is the
the change of the speed which is that to
kind of imitate various speaking style
this is by the way called speed paration
uh in speech recogition and the ESP net
stage two is actually including the
speed of
aeration I think this one is making
it a word should be said here of the
title of Dante's
autobiography yeah that's originally
this one yeah but we just making the
speed lower and then uh this is good
augumentation to include the various the
speaking style and even you know the
sounds like a different speaker right so
it can also be used to consider other
different speaker and so
on so these are kind of a very intuitive
way to the aument the data but the
another kind of important technique uh
developed in the uh the 2019 uh each the
spec
cment uh this is to apply a line uh
mask in the frequency and the time
axis like this so we just the not just
the dropping some kind of portion uh or
just kind of the dropping the some line
that we just drop the uh the completely
uh the this kind of region and then the
uh the uh the question will be the how
how much the D of this one and when we
will kind of apply it and how often we
apply the mask and so on these are kind
of hyper parameters and so one but by
doing this kind of the the LOM the
masking this actually uh the behave to
uh improve the speed quite a lot uh do
training and so during training so by
the way of course we should not do it
during inference right so if you guys
wrly kind of set the the evaluation mode
as a training mode then the the spec
orent for example in ESP net is actually
applied and then this will make the kind
of result disaster so please be careful
about
that and there are lot of kind of
explanation about the the spec arguments
some people may say that you know this
is a kind of imitating the uh the uh
drop of the the speech segment which
happens in the other telecommunication
and so on or the same for the frequency
being and so on but I say that this is
for me very artificial so for me I am
actually regarding it as a more like a
Dropout a random Dropout but the the
speech has some structure and actually
the the just dropping the one frame uh
one the point in the time frequency
being which can be easily uh the
recovered from the other information so
instead using this kind of a structure
uh the uh the information that would be
more kind of a the the strong uh the the
uh the uh information drop uh so that
the the speech U the the recognition
model uh try to make the
robust against this the uh
uh uh masking so that is my personal uh
the the interpretation of the spec
orent uh spec orent is actually
uh for me uh the the the more for the
regularization similar to the Dropout
effect because uh this is a typical
curve of the spec
orent um
the before the spec argument we can
train the model but the validation and
the
training uh the the difference is
actually quite
large uh which means that the the model
is not well
regularized uh but by using the spec
orent we actually can reduce the kind of
the difference of the training the
validation and it's go to kind of uh the
keeping this uh the small uh difference
uh in the training and validation
although uh it uh becomes more EPO to
the the Train the model because uh this
uh the the due to the fluctuation the
training becomes more difficult so this
is a kind of a very typical uh the
behavior of the spec orent and this is
why I kind of saw that explain that the
the spec augment is very similar to the
Dropout Behavior and then the Dropout
also means that the regularization so
this my kind of a interpretation some
other people may have another uh the
interpretation okay so uh this is the uh
the uh the spec orent but the uh
by doing this kind of a smaller uh the
difference we can actually safely train
the model the moox and then it actually
could finally reaching to the better
performance that is mostly I observe we
observe in the spec augment and it
actually has a very significant
Improvement uh this is one the paper
comes from the the the the our teams the
uh the spec orent result but the it's
almost half so in other words you know
the by the way if we make more effort in
some of the regularization optimization
uh that without spec augment it may
reach to the something similar but spec
augment is very
easily making the the performance to be
improved but just we need to wait a
little bit more aox and so
on and uh this is also the result that I
showed before Google the spec arment
actually the having the record number at
that time in
2019 compared with all kind of strong
competitor so this the spec augment
actually makes a big impact in the
community and then right after that many
people actually started to use it as a
standard technique so I'm very sure that
the many of uh the uh the
training the the tools and so on now
supporting the the spec government other
standard the
implementation and I also want to
mention that the data simulation is also
quite stand
it can be included in the framework like
espet actually has the data simulation
on the fly during training we can also
do that but mostly people just kind of
doing the data simulation in advance
offline and then train the model which
is okay sounds good uh next uh move to
the multilingual uh ASR this is ISA
application uh the and then I will
explain about uh the
uh the N2 and Sr and the HM based the
hon based
systems so first I will just want to
recap the hmm buses the end to end
systems and the one of the the big
difference uh is actually whether it
required linguistic resources or not
right and you guys may remember we you
know played with the uh the CMU uh
dictionary right and the uh with this
dictionary uh if we have such kind of
very uh good dictionary we can make the
form based the speech recognition but
the some cases it's not easy right that
we uh that we also had in the uh the the
homework uh we cannot make a perfect the
pronunciation lexan and then maintaining
them is also very
difficult and applied to the other
language and so it's the more difficult
and so on so this is actually uh one of
the bottleneck used to be in speech
condition and the uh this uh the
uh uh the the problem can be actually
largely mitigated by using the the N2
and neural network because we don't need
a pony right uh your current coding
assignment for which uh that you guys
don't use the pon uh the representation
at all right so uh without that actually
you guys can build speech and so on so
this actually the good benefit uh and
then that we will use this nature and
then we can actually hover the new
paradigm in the multilingual ASR after
ASR but I just want to know that this uh
always has a pro and cons I just using
this one as a benefit currently but it's
actually can be a drawback
later okay so uh let's uh start to uh
discuss about the my
experience uh of building the speech
recognition in
Japanese um Japanese was actually not
ASR friendly language whatever it was
yeah now it will be I will explain about
it by the way this is the typical
sentence in Japanese especially it's in
the uh the uh the the technical ter and
then a lot of kind of the issues happens
so first uh the the big uh difference
compared with the some of your language
uh and the some of your some of your
language may not have this issue and
some of your language have the same
issue would that first that there's no
world
boundary so you don't have to you know
consider to read this one but at
least I just want you to check that
there's actually no space so this means
there is no boundary this is very
typical in the East Asian languages by
the way yeah so if we really try to make
it as a world based approaches we
actually have to provide this kind of
space and how to provide it is very
difficult by the way yeah I will to
explain it the second issue is that the
mix of the four scripts um yeah Japan
including the Roman alphabet but
Japanese usually has three scripts uh
yeah we are doing something
wrong we need a three scripts so one is
the originally from the uh China Chinese
character and we also have additional
two scripts and it's actually mixed so
for example uh left part is actually uh
the Chinese character originally Chinese
character so some of you may actually
read that Chinese people may read it and
the black one is the sh based original
Japanese
character and we also have a green one
this is another syllable based the
character but mainly used for the the
poing languages and of course we also
using the the Roman alphabet and so on
so Japanese naturally we the the the H
kind of mixed script the
issues and it's actually also uh depend
on the uh uh many uh issues basically
the uh pronunciation mapping is uh many
to many uh some of the languages uh the
the one to one some of the language are
many to one some of the language one to
many Japanese cases actually it's a lot
of homonyms and the quite a lot of the
mple pronunciation that happens and uh
also the one character has a very
different different
syllable so this
character uh is actually only one
syllable only one for and and this
character not in this example but this
character is actually one two three four
five six 7 8 nine 10 10 for five cable
uh so it's one character but the if we
for example assign the each the speech
frimes to the character it is not
uniform at all yeah more or less that
this happens to the your language as
well because for example consonant and
Bo are very different right uh but the
this is
quite difficult in terms of the
alignment uh and so on and uh how to
solve this kind of problem uh we
actually Japanese researchers uh
developed tokenizer very special toer
which actually jointly solving the world
boundary mix of the the script the
pronunciation program so actually our
tokenizer is uh developed in the of
course it has a long history but our
tokenizer some of the your country your
languages may also have a tokenizer but
the many of them are rule based right
was a very kind of beginning we moved to
the machine learning like a CRF or sbm
and so so on because it's very difficult
so it cannot be solved by by the rule
only and we using that the data manner
uh to solve this kind of problem and so
on and this is actually uh the uh
introducing another issue so actually
the the this means that the if you the
the the uh the the the some of them
using the tokenizer tool a for example
there are several tokenizer the CH
makeup the kitty and so by the way S one
kitty was made by the gr new the the
professor in the the
FDI and if we for example using that if
I use the chassen and the gr using the
kitti and then the result is different
so we couldn't compare the result
actually yeah that's a quite the
difficult the issue and so on so again
the the uh Japanese used to be one of
the most the difficult uh the the uh
languages uh to perform the speech
recognition so we need to have a correct
talker to well spirit and then providing
the the pon otherwise we cannot make
speech and so by the way yeah the
difficult part is that depending on
where we kind of split the word
sometimes pronunciation can also be
changed so this is very kind of we have
to jointly solve this
problem um so this is the actually one
of my the goal the one of the big
research goals when I started speech
which is to remove this kind of
tokenizer so it is actually for me the
dream technology but fortunately in in
my the the the middle career I actually
uh the solve this problem I'm very lucky
to have this kind of a problem by
solving it which is we just using end to
end and then skipping everything and the
directly predicting this four syllable
uh that's it h sorry yeah directory
predicting thisable we don't need talk
nether we don't need pronunciation
dictionary we're just predicting the the
from the speech to uh the the uh the
this kind of the mix of the syllable it
was actually quite working well and the
it my initial attempt is 2016 in the uh
the one database called the Corpus of
spontaneous Japanese and 10% and now
that a lot of kind of effort like a spec
Transformer and so on it actually goes
to 5% or less than 5% uh but end to end
is actually working quite well in this
problem without using the
toer and probably I am the first person
to use the the the without using the
tokenizer to the perform the speech
recogition in Japanese and this again
one of my dreams so one of my dreams I
saw that this cannot be solved in my
entire research life but in just my
middle research career I saw one of my
actually researchs
yeah okay so this is actually great
experience this actually the the single
languages but Japanese has a lot of
issues right and then that means that we
can actually apply the same the
methodology to the
multilingual n to and Sr again Japanese
mix script that this mean that single
model to kind of the deal with the
several script right and also we also
deal with a very
different the the token that may have
different pronunciation and so on it
doesn't matter if the the new network
can handle it we can actually handle the
multilingo uh the the languages so this
is the based on my experience after I
kind of finished the uh this work I
moved to the the MultiLing n and
ASR and before that MultiLing ASR was
not easy for example this is a speech
equ Pipeline and we actually have to
solve the multilingual speech equ by
having a language detector and their own
kind of other languages ASR of course
some part like feature extraction and so
on can be shared but there used to be
acoustic modeling lexicon language model
each buil uh by the using the separate
the ASR system uh and so on it was
actually not easy so this is one reason
that the ASR the team in the big
companies which supporting many
languages used to have to have a many
Engineers that you know each engineer is
actually the taking charge of the SE one
language or several langage and so
on however end to end method could
actually po entially make it a single
the neural network and so
on so how to do that again I didn't do a
special
things I just using the normal speech in
this uh at the time I just using the
hybrid CTC attention that the uh I
explained in the CTC section and then uh
just the ask the expand the
vocabulary with the l
Japanese shik and so on we just expand
vocabulary and then uh we also adding
the character uh the uh language ID
which is the inspired by the machine
translation machine translation people
also putting it here so I kind of
putting the the language the ID token
and so one and then just mix the data
and train the single system uh that's it
so the most of the effort is actually
comes from the uh the the data
preparation and mixing the data
architecture is completely
same and this is actually the great uh
because before we have this methodology
again we have to add the maker the
system for each language and for me the
most of the difficult part is the
dictionary the dictionary is one of the
most difficult part I still remember
that the when I was a company in Japan
and I tried to make a a Wall Street
Journal speech system it took half year
uh mostly we didn't know the English
language you know what kind of resource
we should use and what kind of the
dictionary we should use and even we use
the dictionary there are lot of
redundant pronunciation and we have to
kind of carefully check you know and
then removing it and doing the
experiment doing it again and again and
we finally made the world stre journals
the recipe but I'm sure that now you
guys if you leun the ESP net you guys
can actually make the world journal the
speech easily and then this kind of
effort every language we used to have to
do that but by mixing it and just kind
of predicting the token the character
and then that we can actually mitigate
the issue uh based on the
dictionary so this is the one of my
result uh that we actually making the uh
10 language speech
recogition uh system and collecting the
the 10 languages and the uh we make a
speech conition the system and this one
blue one is language dependent system
the trained by the uh the single end to
end system and that one is just mixing
everything and then perform speech
and we actually found a very good the
performance Improvement by the way this
is err so lower is uh better so most of
the languages actually we have a a very
good Improvement I can explain why
later and another kind of interesting uh
the the the work is that we the also the
augment the token as I explained right
we are putting this kind of
language ID to in the beginning or it
maybe that in the end that doesn't
matter but at that time we actually put
it in the uh beginning in the language
ID and then this is actually very
natural task right speech first
predicting whether this the speech is
English or
Japanese this actually including a
language
predictor and then after that given this
kind about the speech uh the the
language ID T we generating the
corresponding transcriptions which in
this case is English or Japanese and so
on so uh by using this kind of a token
argumentation we can actually combine
the multilingual speech and language in
the one system and again I uh we didn't
change many of the kind of uh the
architecture we just changing the
transcription and adding this kind of
token so this is now probably some
people here are very familiar right
because the whisper or other techniques
are also putting a lot of kind of token
uh in this kind of the sentence and so
on and then probably I am the first be
person to start to use this uh the
language ID token uh in speech uh
recognition although it is already used
in the machine translation but I put
this other kind of uh the language that
I talk in the the beginning which I want
to include language identifier uh the
and speech recogition at the same time
and let's check the kind of performance
this is old result probably we should
have better result uh but this uh is the
uh the the language recognition
performance and the diagonal the higher
means the language ID is correctly
recognized and most of the cases
actually very easily uh the uh the
language ID is well the estimated except
for some kind of uh
the uh some cases like Spanish Italian
uh there are some kind of errors but I
heard from the them that they are kind
of a difficult to uh the distinguish so
this result is uh not very bad in terms
of the uh the con
similarity in the Spanish and Italian
and after that we also appli to the uh
low resource languages uh which is the
actually I couldn't uh these are several
uh one is actually from my computer it
is where the display but when I move to
here and then
displ becomes this so it's not my fault
but a
displ and but anyway yeah I couldn't
read any of them or especially except
for this one uh but it seems like the uh
the this methodology can also be working
on the the L resource the luggage and
the uh this is of course not only our
group there are actually the concurrent
work in the other groups like Google and
so on and later this kind of direction
is very
accelerated uh for example after the uh
the hour work our group actually tried
to kind of expand the language to the
around 90 languages uh the the Maring of
speech
conition and the open there The Whisper
is supporting 99 languages maybe in more
I'm not sure but the at least the
previous version is 99 NES and the uh
next lecture we will also explain about
our decent effort of reproducing the The
Whisper model we call it OS owsm sorry
that is the SP speak correct that
incorrect
owsm we call it awesome model Fe ACC
supporting the 151 languages and the D
the Google the club here so you guys can
actually test your own own languages so
of course it's uh the compared with
whisper uh there are some kind of a
degradation but the supplying is working
quite well at least for English and
Japanese I can do not the uh the uh the
demonstrate it
uh uh but just want to show you that the
the our model awesome is actually
supporting quite many languages so sour
languages
is I say
100 uh
1501 yeah but we are not sure you know
the some of the language just you know
may not work but at least supporting
1501 and
uh I test the Japanese and English and
it's working quite well and if I'm
testing Chinese and it's working well
right yeah these also similar techniques
uh that we just the mixing the data and
adding the language ID
Tab and recently also the meta uh is the
the uh the proposing to deal with 1,000
over 1,000 languages uh this project
called MMS and this uh direction is
quite actively studied
now um and the uh this methodology can
be actually applied to many of other
problem one of the approach is code
switching and it's actually not easy to
get the code switching
data uh how to make it we just
simulating it by concatenating the
multiple language
sentences and then regarding it other
training data and then data stage is
same just other train it with a single
other new Network and hope to perform
the code switching and so on and this
one is also working to some extent it's
not the best result but just kind of
mixing such kind of uh the uh the
simulated code switching data we can
actually the making the uh the code
switching model working and so on and I
have a several demonstration but I can
skip this
yeah and another application
uh of this methodology is the uh
endangered uh language
documentation so this is actually
collaboration with uh the Jonathan the
Amis which used to have guest
lecture here in the Mingo uh NLP two
years ago so he actually corrected uh
the
Euro mistake one of the endangered
languages uh in Mex Meo and it has a
quite difficult transcription bottleneck
and transcriber shortage and so on and
also the the making the pronunciation
lexicon is very difficult uh but by
using the N2 and Sr we can actually
build this endangered language uh the
the the speech system and the
performance is not doesn't reach to the
uh the the exper but at least the
reaching to the Novis transcriber level
which is not bad uh then you know we can
just correcting the uh the it by using
the the exper and so on so uh this uh
kind of multilingual ASR system can also
be used for the the the endangered uh
language documentation uh and so
on and discuss a bit more about the uh
token augumentation
uh the as I said you know we can just
kind of adding the token argumentation
uh token special token here right so
it's actually can be extended many other
kind of speech con system like for
example if we put the speaker ID here if
we know the speaker ID and putting the
speaker ID here we can actually the uh
uh doing the speaker recognition and the
speech eqution at the same time there
are such kind of study exist and the
same for the direct ID and the whisper
especially having the time stamp uh the
function which is kind of providing the
onset and offset of the each sentence uh
this is also the the performing The Bad
and speech at the same time and another
the interesting application is speech
translation and speech translation is
also basically similar style we just
using the uh the probably we are just
using the English and then the
generating the English text but by just
the having
the the the uh Japanese speech as an
input and then prepare the corresponding
Text data and then English as a kind of
the the the specifier of the language
and then we can perform the English to
uh sorry Japanese to English speech
translation and we can combine this two
the other language and so on and then we
can also building the uh
the uh the multilingual uh Speech
translation system uh based on this uh
methodology uh and so on there are lot
of several kind of different
architecture and so on but the basically
uh the technique is quite similar uh by
the way the most different part of the
speech translation and speech equ is
that we have discussed many times the
monotonic uh hard alignment property
monotonic alignment property and so on
so actually speech translation people
don't use CTC or RN transmissor because
of this kind of a problem mostly people
are using the attention based
approach and there are lot of other
token argumentation work other recently
which is actually uh the putting the
some of the uh the intention of the the
text and then jointly kind of the
Performing the speech and spoken
language understanding uh at the same
time uh I also by the way have to
apologize that this the lecture is
speech recognition and understanding but
understanding part is a little bit
shallow but this is because speech is
the most kind of technologically
important and the understanding part is
just kind of extending it and so on
easily by using the classification of
the intention or some other things so
that's why mostly we are putting in the
speech condition
yeah uh by using that the speech spoken
language understanding and speech
recognition joint modeling is also
easily uh realized by based on the token
argumentation and I just want to note
that the my kind of leure
the the the second half of the lecture
basically I didn't change the
architecture just you know preparing the
data data and some kind of additional
token or data orentation and so on and
then we can actually changing the speech
equation functions to the other uh
Speech uh processing uh applications of
course the the some of the system is
still kind of expert uh uh the
the specific to the uh Speech
translation or specific to the speech
recogition but recent trend of the the
speech the technology is try to kind of
unify many of the task by using this the
token argumentation or even the natural
language based prompt like large
language model is doing these are quite
kind of active research areas in the
speech processing similar to the other
areas in NLP computer vision machine
learning and so
on okay
so okay so maybe I can uh concluded the
this
part so uh discussion is whether we
should go with an end to endend Sr
system for any of the
problems one of the biggest kind of the
problem is that St we need to have a a
parallel data to train the
system and this is are very difficult to
correct in general like I mentioned that
you know I was that our group is prepare
providing the endanger language
documentation system based on end to
ASR but this is mostly uh the we just
made a system and it was actually mostly
uh the done by the great effort uh in
the FI study and so on and then they
collect the tons of the data and we can
make it but it is not easy uh also the
uh the transcriptions are the is are the
not standardize in general so we
actually uh have to have a a lot of uh
knowledge to standardize the
transcription and so on uh this is
actually quite difficult part so anyway
the preparing the data it's a kind of a
the one of the biggest the issue in the
speech n to and ASR based speech
condition and there are the two
direction uh the one is the pr trining
fine tuning uh which I will explain it
in the next week and uh the other
approach is that even many cases we even
cannot correct the speech
data in this case can we build a speech
Eon
system it is very difficult but it's
actually possible that I will explain uh
in the next week I plan to explain it
today but I will leave it to the uh in
the next week uh okay uh that's it uh
any
questions okay thank you so much